I'm into art now. I'm drinking from the cup of creativity again. I'm back on track, hooked,
besotted with drawing. It's all I want to do. I think I'm quite good at it, you know, in
a russuesque sort of way. Ivers, my model, I work him to the bone. He's very tolerant,
though. Last week when I asked him to be a nude, descending a stack, as he said.
Who we referencing, bear? Duchamp or Boccioni?
Art. I'm obsessed. I think I'm turning into my sister Beverly. She never liked drawing or
playing with dolls like me. She liked insects, woodlice and beetles. She kept them all in a big
fishbowl. She'd wait until they pegged out and she'd put them in coffins she'd made out of little
raisin boxes. Then she'd bury them in the garden. After a while she'd dig them up to see what had
happened to them. She was really obsessed. Melvin lived next door and one day Bev borrowed
his favorite train set so that her pet mouse, Peter, could ride in it. She'd bride him with
the promise of sexual favor. Bev forced the mouse to drive the train, but she soon got bored with
so she put things on the rails to cause derailments. Catastrophes, she called them.
She got more and more ruthless.
Finally she tried to blow up the level crossing with a firework.
She hoped to bump up the mouse with the carpet caught fire and the mouse turned brown.
But survived. Well, later he did die of trauma.
She gave the mouse the works, a state funeral into the garden.
She played Ravel's Pavan for a dead Infanta on Dad's Dunset record player.
She made us all wear black.
I found these the other day. My first drawings. Oh, I used to draw all the time. I just couldn't
stop. The walls of my bedroom were completely covered with my drawings. I don't know, it was
it was like a drug. I used to get into trouble at school for drawing all the time instead of doing
proper work. Once I got caught drawing our teacher Miss Maps in the nude. She knew it was her.
She recognized the hairs poking through the holes in her stockings. She just went quiet like a mouse.
Oh yeah, Miss Maps. Drawing's all I ever think about now. I draw all the time,
but I still make things for people too. But that last jumper I needed to read,
this little girl. Well, it's lovely barrel. It's really artistic. Only I never saw actually
wearing it. All I ever wanted to do was to go to art school, be creative, have a career. But
then I got pregnant with Colin. Yeah, Colin, another obsessive in the family. One day when
he was young, he brought home this pigeon. It couldn't fly. It had a broken wing. He called it
Percy. Oh, Colin adored Percy. They were inseparable. He did everything for him. It
was a love affair. He even hoisted him up on the clothesline so he could relate to other birds.
He built Percy a state-of-the-art pigeon coop. It had everything. Mezzanine floors,
centered heating run by a steam engine. It was a palace in the garden.
In the house we had nothing. No bathroom and nothing. Colin worshiped Percy. It ended in
tragedy though. He saw the culprit. Colin vowed revenge. The crossbow he made was precision built.
The arrows had Percy's feathers in them. He practiced firing at a particular piece of
wall and waiting. Had waited. Colin shot the cat. It landed in a neighbor's garden.
She was a cat fanatic. She called the police. They called it a crime of passion. Colin got off
with a caution. He's still totally obsessed with precise technical detail. You know,
things like railway signaling system. Same room as his parent when the line is already occupied.
It's Yamaha organ. And screw threads. 12 TPI. Flank angles for metric UNC and UNF screw threads
are 30 degrees. A total thread angle of 60 degrees. And he taught himself to speak Dutch.
I can't believe he's 38 and still lives at home with us.
Girlfriend like a normal bloke. Yeah obsession. The whole family's obsessed to something. Colin,
Beverly, now me. Move. I blame how grandma's influence she was obsessed to with pickling.
Grant preserved everything. Pickled in big jars.
Cabbage, eggs, pigs, trotters, cow's tongues, lambs, cheeks. Nothing was safe from her.
I've loved going to Grant's house just to stare at all the jars.
Especially the beetroot. Sometimes she stole some. I always knew because it left crimson stains on
her hands. She wouldn't wash them for days. She cried when the stains disappeared.
When grandma died, the woman next door came in and laid her out on the table in the living room.
She put pennies on her eyes and a bucket underneath the table with holy water in it.
I saw Bev sneak in.
She stayed in there for hours. Just staring and fiddling with Grant's body.
She wasn't sad though.
When she came out, she said, I kicked the bucket too.
Ma'am did think Bev was a bit strange though. Well we all did. She was quite weird though.
Like when we went to the seaside, she never wanted to play on the beach with me.
She always went to the cockle stall to stare at all the pickled fish. She was entranced.
She saved up to buy a jar of jellydeans. She never actually ate them though.
She just brought them out on special occasions to look at.
I used to find decaying food in a room hidden in drawers.
When I asked her about it, all she said was, there's bread in the British Museum that's
2000 years old. It's a fantastic bear.
She made a necklace out of old dried up carrots with rhinestones stuck in them.
She wore it to a tenth birthday party with earrings made out of dead wasps.
I drew ponies in my scrapbook but Bev had photos of mausoleums, mummies and tombs.
Vladimir.
She told me she had dreams of meeting Lenin in his tomb in Moscow. She idolized him.
Vladimir, Vladimir, where are we going today?
Ah Beverly, Engelmoly. Sorry, I was dreaming I was in London on Primrose Hill eating ice cream.
Can we go to come and have my favorite purushki?
Of course, Beverly. We can't go there now. Take my hand.
Of course it was all fantasy but she was obsessed with him.
She even joined the young commoner's team to get a free trip to Moscow to see his tomb.
But the bus only went as far as East Berlin. So Bev quit the party in disgust.
That's the thing about Bev. She always went for it. Fanatical.
This is a seminal piece. My first dynamic self-portrait. I'm asserting my identity,
making my physical mark. It's a new dawn for me like Bev had when she discovered Trigger.
Trigger gets stuffed in California. Well, that was it, wasn't it?
Suddenly a whole new world opened up before her eyes. Bev stuffed everything after that.
She had a book of instructions. She learned it off by heart.
When her dog Rudy died, she stuffed him too.
Then she put Rudy on the mantelpiece. Mum said, oh thank God, no more dog's doodles.
When Bev was 18, she met this American G.I. Hi, I'm Lester. Can I take your daughter out, sir?
Well, that was it. She married him and moved straight to California.
Didn't last though. Bev spent more time at the Trigger Museum. Well, Lester.
Can you believe this? That's it.
I knew it. She's bloody Trigger-oppy.
After Lester, Bev got through a string of rich husbands and got to the
pile of alimony. She's had three boot jobs, butt deduction, lip collagen, and six face tucks.
And she spent a fortune fixing her teeth. Don't I look fantastic?
Body sculpture, she calls it. She started her first business in L.A., stuffing pets for celebs.
Her latest gig's called Remains to be Seen, High Tech Cryogenics for Richos.
She's big time now.
And what have I done with my life? I'm 59, married with a grown-up geek,
still working in a factory, dreaming about what I should have done.
I could have gone to art school, been somebody, been a contender.
Now it's the bloody change, right? I look like shit. I've lost my looks, my figure's gone.
And to cap it all, the other night I caught Ivor watching one of those twerking videos.
And you know what he said?
Well, to be absolutely honest, I did secretly find off the internet.
But when I got it, well, I spent about two bloody hours with it. But whatever I did, it wouldn't fit.
Oh, fuck it. Why am I doing this shit?
I hate myself. To cap it all, later on, Ivor found it in the packet on the sofa.
What's this? Opened it by mistake, did you, love?
Must be for the girl next door. I'll just take it round, should I?
Oh, you didn't try it on, did you, bear? You did, didn't you?
That's it. I need to hit a bev. She's my rock.
Hi, hon. You okay? I don't know, Bev.
I just lost focus, you know. I got distracted.
Don't worry about it, bear. You just got to take control. It's your life.
I mean, look at me, bear. It's real tough sometimes, but I keep pushing.
Oh, sorry, hon. I got to take this.
Well, hi. Thank you for getting back to me. I hear you want to freeze your mother.
Did you like your mother? We have an economy deal.
I'm sorry, can you hold? Bear, check me out for Christ's sake.
Don't I look fabulous? I'm sculpting myself, my own body.
I'm an exhibit, right? I'm a living gallery.
My body is my art. I got to go, hon.
Just go for it. What are you waiting for?
She's right, though. I just got to go for it.
No more arse in about. Ivor!
How we doing this, bear? Walking or running?
Dynamis knife. Velocity, energy. Speed, love. I want speed.
Here we go.
Oh, dear God.
No, we missed it again, Ivor. Oh, you're obsessed, weren't you?
Come on, I know. It's the movement in between, the moment of change.
I've got to capture it. I'm suffering for your art.
It's hyperfuturism, love. Go for it now. Come on.
Oh, God, I need a cup of tea.
I'm talking live with Beryl Thomas,
whose latest exhibition of drawings opens here tonight.
Beryl. Oh, hello.
Can we start by talking about what informs your work?
Well, I think it was Duchamp or Cage, maybe,
who believed that one should embark on a piece
without necessarily having a conception of its eventual denouement.
It's the process involved that's crucial to the journey that you make, see?
Interesting. It's like you're pushing the female gaze here to extremes
and, in the process, not only objectifying men,
but actually deforming the male body in a quite deliberate, almost vicious way.
Oh, no, no. I completely lose sight of the male form. Sex is not involved.
I'm just looking for what supreme moment of change,
the point of dynamic abstraction, the images in between.
It's what I call hyperfuturism.
God, this vodka's good, no?